<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exact narrative and relation of His Most Sacred Majesties escape from Worcester on the third of September, 1651. Till his arrivall at Paris.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84203</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3662</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1034_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209039</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867947</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867947</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168923</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84203)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168923)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 153:E1034[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exact narrative and relation of His Most Sacred Majesties escape from Worcester on the third of September, 1651. Till his arrivall at Paris.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year, 1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 20".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168923:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EXACT NARRATIVE AND RELATION OF HIS Moſt Sacred MAJESTIES Eſcape from <hi>WORCESTER</hi> on the third of <hi>September,</hi> 1651.</p>
            <p>Till his Arrivall at <hi>PARIS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:168923:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:168923:2"/>
            <head>THE KINGS Eſcape from <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ortune had now twice Counterfeited and double-Gilt the Trophees of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, and its Brazen Trumpet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated <hi>Victory,</hi> betrayed or proſtituted before at <hi>Dunbar,</hi> &amp;now raviſhed at <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cester</hi> by numerous over-powring Force, on that Black and White day <hi>September</hi> the 3d. 1651. in the Duſk of which Fatall Evening, when the aſhamed Sun had bluſh't in his ſetting, and plunged his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffrighted Head into the depth of Luckleſſe <hi>Severn,</hi> and the Night ready to Stain and Spot her guilty Sables with loyal Blood, was attiring her ſelf for the Tragedy; The King whoſe firſt and conſpicuous valorous Eſſay ſo exceeded all compariſon that it cannot but oblige Fate to preſerve that Matchleſſe courage and never again to venture or expoſe it to any Hazard) compelled to Abandon the City of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> (whoſe Fidelity and Affection deſerves
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168923:3"/>Perpetual Memory,) after he had quitted his Court and Lodgings to which he retired from the Field, having rallied his moſt Faithful and Conſiderable Friends, divers Engliſh Lords and Gentlemen, who were reſolved to accompany him in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ght; was preſented by that renowned Earle of <hi>Deroy</hi> with one <hi>Charles Gifford</hi> Eſquire, (a perſon of note then of that Country and of much manifeſted Honour ſince to the World) to be his Majeſtic Conductor in this Miraculous, bleſſed Eſcape: who forthwith called for one <hi>Francis Yates,</hi> whom he had brought with him under the Command of Colonel <hi>Careluſſe</hi> in a party that met the KING in his Advance to <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> to be guide-aſſiſtant for the ſurer finding the by ways for his Majeſties ſpeed and ſafety.</p>
            <p>In the mean time Colonel <hi>Carleſſe</hi> (a Gentleman of very Gallant and Noble Endowments) was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to ſuſtain the Brunt of the purſuing Enemy, and to keep them off while the KING might be ſomewhat in his way; which with excellent Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Valour he did to effect, and afterwards fled to his old retract and coverture, paſſing by <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlebury</hi> Caſtle, then Garriſond by the Enemy, whom he Couragiouſly Fought with and broke through, and came ſafe to his Deſigned ſhelter.</p>
            <p>Towards three a Clock <hi>Thursday</hi> morning the 4 of <hi>September,</hi> the KING in company with the ſaid Earle of <hi>Derby,</hi> Earle of <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> Earle of <hi>Cleave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> my Lord <hi>Wilmot,</hi> and others to the number of Fourſcor came to the place called <hi>White-Ladies</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Tong</hi> in the confines of <hi>Stafford</hi> and <hi>Shropſhire,</hi> being 25 miles
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168923:3"/>diſtant or there abouts from <hi>Worceſter,</hi> which ſpace of ground he had rid that night.</p>
            <p>This <hi>White-Ladies</hi> was a houſe belonging to one <hi>Fitz Harbert,</hi> where one <hi>George Pendril</hi> (the young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Brother of the five who were all ſeverally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental in the conductment and preſervation of his Majeſty) hearing ſomebody knocking at the Gate ſo early, opening the Window he eſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there the aforeſaid <hi>Francis Yates,</hi> who was his brother in Law, with Mr. <hi>Gifford;</hi> to whom he preſently opened the door, and enquired of his brother <hi>Yates</hi> what News from <hi>Worceſter,</hi> who told him that the KING was Defeated and in Purſuite, and therefore bid him to make haſt and put on his Cloaths. But before he could make himſelf ready, the King with moſt of his Lords had entred the houſe, and came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Hall, where after a ſhort conſultation held among them, the Earle of <hi>Derby</hi> called for <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Pendrill</hi> the Eldeſt brother, (you muſt know that my Lord of <hi>Derby</hi> had taken this place for a ſubterfuge, after the defeat given him by Colonel <hi>Lilburn</hi> neer <hi>Wigan</hi> in <hi>Lanchaſhire,</hi> and was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted there, and by them conveyed to <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> to the King; as alſo ſeveral other Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men before had uſed this for their Sanctuary) who being come, <hi>George</hi> was ſent to <hi>Tong</hi> to one <hi>Robert Beard</hi> an Honeſt Subject to enquire of him whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there were any ſcattered parties of the Kings thereabouts, or any of the Enemies appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; who brought word that the Coaſt was yet clear and no parties at all to be ſeen. In his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn he met with his Brother <hi>Richard;</hi> for now
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168923:4"/>thoſe few Inhabitants that Lived there, were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakned with the Noyſe, and their own ill bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thoughts and fears of the ſucceſſe at <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard</hi> was no ſooner come in, but Squire <hi>Gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> called for him, and bad him make haſt, and bring with him his beſt Cloaths, which were a Jump and Breeches of Green courſe Cloth and a Doe ſkin Leather Doublet, the Hat was bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed of <hi>Humphrey Pendrill</hi> the Miller being an old Gray one that turned up its Brims—the Shirt (which in that Countrey Language they call'd an Hurden or Noggen Shirt, of Cloath that is made of the courſeſt of the Hemp,) was had of one <hi>Edward Martin, George Pendrills</hi> Bond, and <hi>William Creſwells</hi> Shoos; which the King having preſently unſtripped himſelf of his own Cloaths, did nimbly d'on. His Buffe Coat, and Linnen Doublet, and a Gray pair of Breeches which he wore before, he gave into theſe Brothers Hands, who forthwith buried them under ground, where they lay five weeks, before they durſt take them up again. The Jewels off his Arm he gave to one of the Lords then departing.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>Richard</hi> came with a pair of Shears and rounded the King's hair, which my Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> having cut before with a Knife, had untowardly notched; and the King was pleaſed to take notice of <hi>Richards</hi> good barbing, ſo as to prefer his work before my Lord <hi>Wilmots,</hi> and gave him the praiſe of it; and now his Majeſty was <hi>Alamode</hi> the Woodman.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:168923:4"/>
            <p>Hereupon <hi>William Pendril</hi> was brought to the King by the Earl of <hi>Derby,</hi> and the care and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of his moſt ſacred Majeſty committed to his charge and the reſt of the Brothers, (any Lord would have ſtaid too but there was no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking ſecurity for them both) and preſently the Lords took their heavy leave and departed, every one ſhifting for himſelf. Onely my Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> was conveyed by <hi>John Pendrill</hi> to Mr. <hi>Thomas Whitgreaves,</hi> but he would have left him at ſeveral other places wich my Lord did in no wiſe approve of; firſt at one <hi>John Shores</hi> of <hi>Hungerhill,</hi> thence to <hi>John Climpſon,</hi> thence to one <hi>Reynolds</hi> of the <hi>Hide,</hi> ſo to <hi>John Humſpaiches,</hi> where paſſing by <hi>Coven,</hi> they had notice of Troop of Horſe in the Town, and ſeeing ſome men coming behind them, (which proved to be Friends, though my Lord ſuſpected the Country riſe upon them) they betooke themſelves into a dry pit, where they ſtayed till Evening, and then arrived ſafely at Mr. <hi>Whitgreaves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Company being all departed, a Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bill was brought, and put into the Kings hand, and he went out with <hi>Richard</hi> into the adjoining Woods. <hi>VVilliam</hi> departed home and <hi>Humphrey</hi> and <hi>George</hi> went out to ſcout, and lay hovering in the Woods to hear or ſee if any one approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched that way. But the King had not been an hour in the Wood, before a Troop of Horſe of the Enemies came to <hi>VVhit-ladies,</hi> and enquired, if ſome of the Kings Horſe and himſelf paſſed not that way, and if they could give any Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiou of him; to which the Towneſ-folks an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168923:5"/>that about 3 hours ago there was a Party of Horſe came thither, and they ſuppoſed the King with them, but they made no ſtay in the Village, but preſently departed; they were here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſo eager in the purſuit that after enquiring which way they took, they followed the rout, and made no further ſearch there. The King ſtraight heard this by the two aforeſaid Scouts, who ſtragled for Intelligence into the Town.</p>
            <p>All this day, being <hi>Thurſday,</hi> the King conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in the Wood upon the ground, <hi>Richard Pendrill</hi> being conſtantly with him, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the other two Brothers: It proved to be a very rainy day, and the King was wet with ſhowers, thereupon <hi>Francis Yates</hi> his wife came into the Wood and brought the King a Blanket, which ſhe threw over his ſhoulders, to keep him dry; ſhe alſo brought him his firſt meat he eat there, <hi>viz.</hi> a Meſſe of Milk, Eggs and Sugar in a black earthen Cup, which the King gueſſed to be Milk and Apples, and ſaid, he loved it very well; after he had drank ſome of it and eaten part in a pewter Spoon, he gave the reſt to <hi>George</hi> and bid him eat; for it was very good. There was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of moment paſſed this day in Court but only the King exchanged his Wood bill for <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Yates</hi> Broom <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ook,</hi> which was ſomething lighter.</p>
            <p>They had much adoe all that day to teach and faſhion his Majeſty to their Country guiſe, and to order his ſteps and ſtraight body to a lobbing, jobſons gate, and were forced every foot to mind him of it; for the Language, his Majeſties moſt gracious converſe with his People in his Journey to, and at <hi>VVorceſter,</hi> had rendred it very eaſie and very tunable to him.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:168923:5"/>
            <p>About 5. a clock that Evening, the King with the retinue of <hi>Richard, Humphrey, George,</hi> and <hi>Francis Yates</hi> left the wood, and betook himſelf to <hi>Richards</hi> houſe, where he went under the name of <hi>William Jones,</hi> a woodcutter newly come thither for work; againſt his coming, the good wife for his entertainment at ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, was preparing a <hi>Fricaſse</hi> of Bacon and Eggs, and while that was doing, the King held on his knee their daughter <hi>Nan:</hi> after he had eat a little, he asked <hi>Richard</hi> to eat, who replied, yea Sir I will, whereto His Majeſty anſwered, you have a better ſtomach then I, for you have eaten five times to day already. After ſupper ended, the King according to his reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to paſſe into <hi>Wales,</hi> prepared (when it ſhould be dusky) to depart; before he went, <hi>Jane Pendryll</hi> the Mother of the five brethren, came to ſee the King, before whom ſhe bleſſed God that had ſo honoured her Children in making them the inſtruments (as ſhe hoped) of his Majeſties ſafeguard and deliverance. Here <hi>Francis Yates</hi> offered the King thirty ſhillings in ſilver, the King accepted ten, and bad him put the other up. <hi>Humphrey</hi> would have gone before to ſee and view about, but the King would not let him; it being now near night, they took their leave of the King upon their knees, beſeeching God to guide and bleſſe him.</p>
            <p>So the King and <hi>Richard</hi> only, departed to go to one Mr. <hi>Francis Wolfe</hi> of <hi>Madeley,</hi> there to take paſſage into <hi>Wales.</hi> On the way they were to paſſe by a Mill, at a place called <hi>Evelin,</hi> and going over ('twas about nine a clock at night) the bridge of the ſaid Mill, the Milner ſteps forth, and demanded, who goes there?
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168923:6"/>having a quarterſtaffe or a good cudgel in his hand, to which <hi>Richard</hi> being formoſt thought it not ſafe to reply, but the water being ſhallow, leapt of the bridge into it, and the King did the like, following <hi>Richard</hi> by the noyſe and ratling of his leather bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; the Milner being glad he was ſo rid of them; for (as it afterwards appeared) here was ſome of the Kings ſcattered Souldiers in his Mill, and he ſuppoſed the other to be <hi>Parliamentarians</hi> that were upon the ſcent for his diſtreſſed gueſts.</p>
            <p>Being come to <hi>Madely</hi> to the ſaid Maſter <hi>Francis Wolfes</hi> late that Night, they underſtood there was no paſſage over the water into <hi>Wales,</hi> and that it was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dangerous to abide there, the Countrey being e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where about laid with ſouldiers, nor durſt he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain them into his Houſe, but ſhewed them a Hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mow where they might lodge; and there the King and <hi>Richard</hi> continued all that night, and the next day being <hi>Friday,</hi> and that night with the conveyance of a Maid of this Maſter <hi>Wolfes,</hi> who brought the King two miles on his way, they retreated back again to <hi>Richards</hi> Houſe: Mr. <hi>Wolfe</hi> lent the King ſome ſmall ſum of money.</p>
            <p>This deſign being croſſed, <hi>Saturday</hi> morning with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſtay at <hi>Richards,</hi> the King and he went to a Houſe of Miſtris <hi>Giffards,</hi> called <hi>Boſcabell,</hi> where <hi>William Bendril</hi> and his wife dwelt as Houſe-keepers for the ſaid <hi>Giffard,</hi> who received him joyfully; but the Kings feet were ſo bliſtered with travelling in ſuch courſe and ſtiffe accoutrements as he wore on his feet, and lying in them, that he was ſcarce able to ſtand or go, which <hi>Williams</hi> wife perceiving, ſhe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168923:6"/>ſtript off his ſtockins and cut the bliſters, and waſhed his feet, and gave the King ſome Eaſe.</p>
            <p>The ſame time or near thereupon, that Noble Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Careleſſe,</hi> who as is ſaid before made good the Kings Rear at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and had fought his way through, after he had been two dayes at one <hi>David Jones</hi> living in the <hi>Heath</hi> in <hi>Tong-Pariſh,</hi> and there by him ſecured, (for this Col. had lain 3 quarters of a year before obſcured in this Countrey, when he had been narrowly every where ſearcht after was brought by one <hi>Elizabeth Burgeſſe</hi> to this ſame Houſe of <hi>Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabell;</hi> and there His Majeſty and he met, but the Col. was ſo overjoyed with the ſight of the King his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in ſuch ſure and ſafe hands, that he could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frain weeping, and the king was himſelf ſomething moved with the ſame paſſion.</p>
            <p>After a ſhort conference and but inchoated coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of the Kings probableſt means of eſcape, it was reſolved by them to betake themſelves to the wood again; and accordingly about nine of the clock that <hi>Saturday</hi> morning the 6. of <hi>September</hi> they went into the wood, and Col. <hi>Careleſſe</hi> brought and led the King to that ſo much celebrated Oake, where before he had himſelf been lodged: (This Tree is not hollow but of a ſound firm Trunk, onely about the middle of the body of it there is a hole in it about the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a mans head, from whence it abſurdly and abuſively (in reſpect of its deſerved perpetual growth to outlaſt Time it ſelf) is called Hollow; and by the help of <hi>William Pendrils</hi> wood-ladder they got up into the boughs and branches of the Tree, which were very thick and well ſpread, and full of leaves;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168923:7"/>ſo that it was impoſſible for any one to diſcerne through them.</p>
            <p>When they were both up, <hi>William</hi> gave them up two pillows to ly upon between the thickeſt of the branches, and the King being overwearied with his travel and ſore journey, began to be very ſleepy; The Col. to accommodate him the beſt he could, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired his Majeſty to lay his head in his lap, and reſt the other parts of his body upon the pillow, which the King did; and after he had taken a good nap, (<hi>William,</hi> and his wife <hi>Joane</hi> ſtill peaking up and down, and ſhe commonly near the place with a nutt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hook in her hand gathering of ſticks) awaked very hungry, and wiſhed he had ſomething to eat: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Col. pluckt out of his pocket a good lun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chion of bread and cheefe, which <hi>Joane Pendrill</hi> had given him for porvant for that day, and had wrapt it up in a clean linnen cloth, of which the King fed ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry heartily, and was well pleaſed with the ſervice, and commended highly his good chear; and ſome other ſmal relief he had, which was put up into the Tree with a long hook-ſtick.</p>
            <p>In the mean while <hi>Richard Pendrill</hi> (the firſt Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire) was ſent to <hi>Woller-Hampton</hi> ſome three miles thence being a Market Town, to buy Wine and Bisket, and ſome other neceſſary refreſhments for the King; and withal to ſpeak with one Mr. <hi>George Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring,</hi> a perſon of known Integrity and Loyalty from Col. <hi>Careleſſe,</hi> with ſome inſtructions about the Kings removal, though not expreſly the King, but one of that ruined Party: in effect it was to know of him, whether he knew of any ſure privacy for 2 ſuch
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168923:7"/>perſons? to which he anſwered he had not himſelf, but would enquire if a friend of his, one Maſter <hi>Whitgreave</hi> of <hi>Moſeley</hi> formerly and again to be ſpok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en of here) could do it. (So that we may ſee what a Loyal honeſt combination and ſecrecy there was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween all of theſe perſons;) and then <hi>Richard</hi> return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his Wine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the King; who towards the Evening came down by the ſame ladder from the Tree, and was brought into the Garden of <hi>Boſcable</hi> Houſe, where he ſate in the Bower of it, and dranke part of the Wine till toward night.</p>
            <p>Neither was <hi>Humphrey Pendrill</hi> the Miller un-em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed all this while, but was ſent to get intelligence how things went. And the eaſilier to come by it, he was ſent to a Captain of the <hi>Rump</hi> one <hi>Broadways,</hi> formerly a Heelmaker, under pretence of carrying him twenty ſhillings for the pay of a man in the new raiſed <hi>Militia</hi> of their County for their Miſtres. While he was there in came a Colonel of the <hi>Rebels,</hi> and asked for Captain <hi>Broadway,</hi> on purpoſe to know what further enquiry had been made at <hi>White-Ladies</hi> for the King, relating to <hi>Broadway</hi> the Story of it; to which he replyed he knew nothing of it further then rumour, but that there was one of that place in the Houſe that could give him an account of it. So <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrey</hi> was called, and ſeveral queſtions put to him, which he evaded, but confeſt that the King had been there as was ſuppoſed, but there was no likelyhood for him to ſtay there, for there was three Families in the Houſe, and all at difference with one another. The Col. told him there was a thouſand pound offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to any that would take or diſcover him, and that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168923:8"/>they doubted not, but within a day or two to have him delivered into their hands.</p>
            <p>Theſe tydings <hi>Humphrey</hi> brought with him, and omitted not to tell his Majeſty of the price his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells had ſet on him; at the telling of which, the King looked ſomething diſmayed, as having truſted his Life into the hands of ſuch poor Men, whom ſuch a ſumme as that, (though both deteſtable, and of inconſiderable value to the Purchaſe) might pervert from their Allegiance and Fidelity: which made <hi>Humphrey</hi> to be exceedingly troubled for his raſhneſs, while Collonel <hi>Careleſſe</hi> aſſured the King, if it were 100000 l. it were to no more purpoſe, and that he would engage his Soul for their truth; which <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrey</hi> alſo with many urgent aſſeverations did ſecond.</p>
            <p>It was late, and the King was very hungry, and had a minde to a Loyn of Mutton, and being come into the Houſe, asked <hi>William</hi> if he could not get him ſuch a Joynt, to which he replyed, that he had it not of his own, but he would make bold at that time, and for that occaſion, with one of his Maſters Sheep in the Cote; which inſtantly he did, and brought it into the ground Cellar; where the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel not having the patience to ſtay while he fetcht a Knife, ſtabb'd it with his Dagger; and when <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> came down they hung it upon a door, and <hi>fleyd</hi> it, and brought up a hind Quarter to the King, who preſently fell a chopping of the Line to pieces, or (as they called it then) into Scotch Collops, which the Collonel clapt into the Pan while the King held it and fryed it.</p>
            <p>This paſſage yeilded the King a pleaſant jocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168923:8"/>diſcourſe, after his Arrival in <hi>France,</hi> when it amounted to a Queſtion, (a very difficult caſe) who was Cook, and who was Scullion? and for ſolution of the doubt, when it could not be decided by the Lords then preſent, was referred to the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Majeſties Maſter Cook, who affirmed that the king was <hi>hîc &amp; nunc,</hi> both of them.</p>
            <p>When this nimble Collation was ended, it was time for the King to betake himſelf to his reſt, and his Chamberlain <hi>William</hi> brought him to his apparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. It was a place made between two Walls, on purpoſe for ſecrecy, contrived at the building of the Houſe; thither they let the King down, where be ſlept very incommodiouſly with little or no reſt, for that the place was not long enough for him, and therefore the next night they laid him a ſorry Bed upon the Stair-caſe, as they uſed to do for ſtrange Woodcutters, that the meanneſſe of his lodging might ſecure him from ſuſpicion.</p>
            <p>My Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> as is ſaid before, was all this while ſafe at Maſter <hi>Whitgreaves,</hi> onely his care of the King made him full of trouble. His hiding place was ſo ſure a one, that at his firſt coming to it, he wiſhed ſo he gave 20000 l. that the King were ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as ſecure, or there with him; he therefore diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched away <hi>John Pendrill</hi> (who had attended him all along) to the <hi>White Ladies,</hi> to enquire for the King, and to give him notice of the conveniency that was at Maſter <hi>Whitegreaves;</hi> but when he came thither, which was on Friday, the King was then gone to <hi>Madeley,</hi> to Maſter <hi>Wolfes.</hi> The next day he was ſent againe, and by <hi>Richards</hi> Wife directed to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168923:9"/>
               <hi>Boſcabel,</hi> where he delivered the King the Meſſage, which the King aſſented unto, and reſolved to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move thither.</p>
            <p>Munday night, <hi>September</hi> 8. at eleven at night, was the time appointed for the Kings progreſſe to <hi>Moſeley,</hi> but a Horſe was hard to be found. <hi>John</hi> was ordered to borrow one of one <hi>Stanton</hi> of <hi>Hatton,</hi> but he had lent his out before; when the Collonel remembred that <hi>Humphrey</hi> the Miller had one, and he thereupon was called and deſired to lend him for the Kings Service; it was a kinde of War-horſe, that had carryed many a load of proviſion, Meal and ſuch like, but now he put upon him a Bridle and Saddle, that had out-worn its Tree and Irons, and at the time prefixed brought him to the Gate.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as the King had notice of it, out he came, and would have had none but Collonel <hi>Careleſſe,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> to have gone along with him, but they told him, it was very dangerous to venture himſelfe with ſo few, they therefore intreated his Majeſty that he would give them leave to go with him, which at their importunity he granted.</p>
            <p>Having mounted the King, Collonel <hi>Careleſſe</hi> and the ſix brethren guarding him, two before, and two behinde, and one of each ſide, armed with Clubs and Bills (<hi>Humphrey,</hi> leading his Horſe by the Bridle) they began their journey. It was five miles from <hi>Boſcabel</hi> to <hi>Moſely</hi> Maſter <hi>Whitgreaves,</hi> and the way in ſome places miry, where the Horſe blundering, cauſed the King to ſuſpect falling, and bid <hi>Humphrey</hi> have a care, to which he anſwered, that that now fortunate Horſe had carried many a heavier weight
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168923:9"/>his time, ſix ſtrike of Corn (which meaſure the King underſtood not) but now had a better price on his back, the price of three Kingdomes, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore would not now ſhame his Maſter.</p>
            <p>Their travel was ſoon and ſafe ended, and the King brought the back way to a ſtile that led to the Houſe, <hi>Humphries</hi> led the Horſe into a Ditch, and the King alighted off upon the ſtile; but forgetting that moſt of his Guard were to return home, was gone five or ſix ſteps onward, without taking leave of them, but recalling himſelf returned back and ſaid, I am troubled that I forget to take my leave of my friends; but if ever I come into <hi>England</hi> by fair or foul means, I will remember you, and let me ſee you when ever it ſhall ſo pleaſe God; ſo they all kiſſed his Hand and departed, but the Collonel, <hi>John,</hi> and <hi>Francis Yates,</hi> who guided the King to the Houſe.</p>
            <p>There Maſter <hi>Thomas Whitgreave</hi> received the King dutifully and affectionately, and brought him in to my Lord <hi>Wilmot,</hi> who with infinite gladneſſe, kneeled down and embraced his knees. After a little conference, his Majeſty was had to his lodging, and the intriques of it ſhown him; where after the King had reſted himſelfe that night, they entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to conſultation about the eſcape, which had been projected by my Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Francis Yates</hi> departed, but <hi>John</hi> ſtaid two or three dayes longer with the King, while he went away. On Wedneſday noon a Troop of the Rebels horſe paſſed through the Town and made no ſtay, which <hi>John</hi> told not the King of till after noon, becauſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168923:10"/>(as he then ſaid) he would not ſpoil his Majeſties Dinner.</p>
            <p>Now the King prepared and fitted himſelf for his journey, and one Mr. <hi>Huddleſtone</hi> and Maſter <hi>VVhit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greave</hi> accommodated him with Boots, Cloak, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, &amp;c. and <hi>Iohn Pendril</hi> was ſent to Miſtreſſe <hi>Lane</hi> about it, who ſent him back again with a parcel of leaves of Walnuts, boyled in Spring Water, to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour his Majeſties hands, and alter the hue and white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his Skin in thoſe places that were moſt obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the eye, and by him gave notice to the King, what time ſhe ſhould be ready.</p>
            <p>On Thurſday night the eleventh of <hi>September,</hi> Collonel <hi>Lane</hi> came with his Siſter to a field adjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and there they put the King before her. <hi>Iohn</hi> having the honour to hold the Kings Stirrup while he mounted, and preſently they two ſet forward, (having taken directions to know the Countrey) and my Lady <hi>Lane</hi> having ſeveral recommendations to the allyes, friends and acquaintance of her family, that lay in their intended road, if any untoward oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion ſhould put them to the tryal.</p>
            <p>The ſeveral adventures which that Heroical Lady paſſed and overcame, in the management of that grand affair of his Majeſties life, will become and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit a worthier Paper, and a Nobler Pen, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let the bleſſed and thrice happy event of that her fortunate Loyalty, reſtrain a curious enquiry of the means, which probably may be ſome <hi>arcana imperii,</hi> ſecrecy of State now, as well as then of the King, not yet fit to be divulged. Miracles indeed of this benigne and propitious influence are very rare (God
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168923:10"/>hath not dealt ſo with the Nations round about us) Eſpecially where Humane Coadjument, and that ſo ſignally (in the taciteneſſe of ſo many perſons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned) hath been inſtrumental; and therefore why may we not (as we fearfully behold Comets) with delight look upon the ſerene ſmiles of Heaven (in His Majeſties preſervation) and the Rayes of its Goodneſſe diffuſed into the Breaſts of thoſe Loyal Perſons his Guardians, (for whoſe Honour more eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially this Paper officiouſly obtrudes it ſelf) with ſuch weak eyes as we now ſee with, before we can have the benefit of a proſpective (the full Relation)</p>
            <p>Let it therefore ſuffice and content us, that it pleaſed the Divine Wiſedome and Goodneſs to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect and defend our moſt gracious Soveraign in all dangers and places and conditions whatſoever, in that his incumbred paſſage through his own rightful Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, and without the leaſt umbrage of ſuſpition, to conveigh him out of the hands of his blood-thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty Trayterous Enemies, who thought themſelves ſure of Him, <hi>That ſo killing the Heir, the Inheritance might be theirs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He remained or rather Pilgrimaged from one Sanctuary to another in <hi>England</hi> near the ſpace of five weeks, and like other Princes, though not on the ſame Account was preſent <hi>incognito</hi> while ſuch time as a Convenience of Paſſage could be found for him in <hi>Suſſex,</hi> where after he had Embarqued Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in a Barke out of a Creek, He was put back a-again by contrary weather into the ſame place, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſguiſed in a <hi>Saylors cloaths;</hi> but the wind veer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168923:11"/>about more favourably about the end of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> 1651. Landed at <hi>Deep</hi> in <hi>Normandy,</hi> from whence an Expreſſe was ſent to her Majeſty of <hi>England,</hi> to acquaint her of His ſafe Arrival, which was preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly communicated to the <hi>French</hi> Court, who appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly with great Manifeſtation of Joy welcomed the Newes: But His Majeſties moſt Affectionate Uncle, the late Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> did with entire joy, As alſo ſundry of the moſt eminent <hi>French</hi> Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, Congratulate His Deliverance, which they te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by a moſt Splendid and Honourable <hi>Cavalcade</hi> at His Reception and Entry into <hi>PARIS.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
